<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fig for the Spaniard, or Spanish spirits VVherein are liuelie portraihed the damnable deeds, miserable murders, and monstrous massacres of the cursed Spaniard. With a true rehearsal of the late trobles, and troblesome estate of Aragon, Catalonia, Valencia, and Portingall: Wherevnto are annexed matters of much marueile, and causes of nolesse consequence. Magna est veritas, &amp; preualet.</title>
            <author>G. B., fl. 1592-1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116564</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851780</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17071</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00209)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17071)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 711:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fig for the Spaniard, or Spanish spirits VVherein are liuelie portraihed the damnable deeds, miserable murders, and monstrous massacres of the cursed Spaniard. With a true rehearsal of the late trobles, and troblesome estate of Aragon, Catalonia, Valencia, and Portingall: Wherevnto are annexed matters of much marueile, and causes of nolesse consequence. Magna est veritas, &amp; preualet.</title>
                  <author>G. B., fl. 1592-1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Woolfe, and are to be solde by william Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: G. B.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-A1, D4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  History --  Philip II, 1556-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:1"/>
            <p>A FIG FOR THE SPANIARD, OR SPANISH SPIRITS.</p>
            <p>VVherein are liuelie portraihed the <hi>damnable deeds, miſerable murders, and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous</hi> maſſacres of the curſed Spaniard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a true rehearſal of the late trobles, and troble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> eſtate of Aragon, Catalonia, Valencia, <hi>and Portingall:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherevnto are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of much marueile, and cauſes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt veritas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> praeualet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Woolfe,</hi> and are to <hi>be ſolde by william Wright.</hi> 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CVRTEOVS GENTLEMEN REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERS, HEALTH.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, though</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip <hi>of Spaine be olde and bed-redde yet hee is not quite dead, and though his forces for the preſent be ſomewhat weakned, yet is hee not vtterly conquered: in good time hee may be by diuine aſsistance, and your worthy valors, ſhew your ſelues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right inheritours of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of your aunceſtours: that is, in peace to be mindful of warre, and in war moſt studious of peace, bearing</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17071:3"/> 
               <hi>alwaies vpright minds, and forward heartes, to helpe your friendly neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. For if our friendly neighbors farewell, then like all friends we ſhal fare the better, but if they faile of peaceable ſucceſse, wee can looke for nothing but warlike vproares: your wiſedomes know what I meane, let it be then brieflie, pro lege, pro rege, pro grege: Macte virtute ſitis.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours at commandement, G. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="envoy">
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>HAec eſt virgo poteus, haec eſt Regina fidelis,</l>
               <l>Haec eſt Diua latens muliebribus alma figuris,</l>
               <l>Quae tot luſtra gerens apud Anglos nobile ſceptrum,</l>
               <l>Regibus eſt redamata bonis, populo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Deo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>LENVOY.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>ONe thing remaines thee (Reader) yet vndone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſt vp thine eyes, and ſee her ſplendent grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whome Graces ſo adorne that ſhe hath wonne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From Monarkes all the firſt and higheſt place:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And raignes on Earth like Goddeſſe ſent from loue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In mercie, peace, proſperitie, and loue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>To her for ſuccour, kings do flie from farre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No king (ſaue one) but ioyes our Sabaes plight,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:17071:4"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Poore ſtrangers from their ſoyles expeld by warre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Chriſtes ſake, find fauour in her ſight:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From North, from South, from Eaſt, and from the Weſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To hir they come, and heere they finde a reſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>O happie Realme, where mercie beareth ſwaie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O happie Realme, where Hypocrites auaunt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such Hypocrites I meane, that counſayle aye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nought els but death, and Princes braines inchant:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such Hypocrites in Fryers habites lurke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That rapines, rapes, treaſons, guyles, murders worke.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aske</hi> France <hi>heereof, ſuch Hypocrites they rue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And</hi> England <hi>when king</hi> Iohn <hi>was poyſoned:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her Maieſtie hath found it too too true</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But</hi> Ioue <hi>hath vow'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaue his daughters head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ioue <hi>her defend from all ſuch monſters fell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And from the Romiſh monſter, that monſtrous feend of hell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Pro Lege, pro Rege, pro Groge.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:4"/>
            <head>A FIG FOR THE Spaniard.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath bene ſeene from the hegin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note place="margin">There hath bene alwaies from time to time, a trouble<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome people in the world, and great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſters of their neighbours, exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples folow.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is proued moſt true, that among the nations there hath alwaies beene one ſeuerall people, farre ſurpaſſing the other in ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious price, and tyrannicall policy, not ſeeking by neighborhood to quench their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull thirſt to rule: but quickning the flames of their vnnaturall dropſie by hawty rage, the one purchaſing them deadly hatred abroad, the other continuall tumults at home, both endleſſe vnquiet of their reſtles thoughts.</p>
            <p>In the greene ſpring of the worlde (what time <note place="margin">In the ſecond raigne of Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiel ſpirite of Saturne. The pride &amp; tyranny of nimrod, ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the ſeede of Cham.</note> ambition thruſting out her monſtrous head, began freſhly to ſow common diſcord among men, and general contempt of God himſelfe.) <hi>Nimrod</hi> of the ſeed of curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> tearmed in holy writ a ſtrong hunter: that is, ſuch a one as compelled men to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay, either by force, or for feare, in loftines of mind forgetting himſelfe to be mortall, and faining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and fellowe Princes immortall, by ouer-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring his ſimple neighbours, reared a tower, whoſe ſtrange height might match the top of heauen, and
<pb facs="tcp:17071:5"/> conſequently (like God) ouer-looke the whole earth. But as he that ſitteth aboue the Cherubins, and laugheth to ſcorne the fond deuices of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges, with woonderfull patience pampreth the proud a while, and ſuffreth them like coped Lyons to ſwing their ſhort courſe, ſo when they begin to grow intollerable, neuer was their lift ſo lofty, but their fall is as low, if not lower, to the loweſt nook of hell.</p>
            <p>A preſent and perfect mirrour is this Nimrod, who when he had tyrannized ouer his commons, <note place="margin">The effects of tyranny.</note> vſurped ouer his neighbors, foraged their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, neglected diuine rites extinguiſhed true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and in the mount of his pride (for ſuch is the inſatiable and ſwelling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>come of ambition) op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelfe againſt God, was ſuddenly thrown <note place="margin">The fall of Nimrod firſt king of the world, and Emperour of the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> downe, deſpoiled of his Crowne, his glorie rent from him, his Maieſtie impaired, his dominions tranſlated, and all his ſtocke defaced by <hi>Aſsur,</hi> of whome proceeded afterward the Monarchie, and maſterdome of the Aſſirrians. Theſe gallants en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying the Empire, and his Metropolis Babilon, <note place="margin">The example of the Aſſiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans proceding of Aſſur.</note> more yeares then <hi>Nimrod,</hi> but with no leſſe pride, thought it no offence with <hi>Nimrod</hi> to opreſſe their ſubjects, rob and ſpoile their friends, depopulate forraine countries, ſlaughter their neighbours, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpe ouer their Territories, and count all lawefull pillage which their ſwords could wrongfully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe.</p>
            <p>But as theſe caualiers dealt with the Chaldeans, <note place="margin">Such meaſure as we meat to others, ſuch meaſure ſhall be met to vs.</note> ſo likewiſe are they meaſured vnto, and matched by the Medes, who perceiuing their diſcipline of
<pb facs="tcp:17071:5"/> warre, changed altogeather into delicate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, their wealth reapt by proweſſe, rupt on the backes of ſtrumpets, and that their riches made them rechleſſe, more apt to take their preſent caſe, then to delight in their former exploits, tooke har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie grace, ſuddenly inuaded them, ſpeedily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered <note place="margin">The originall of the Median Monarchie, in the fal of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Sardana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palus.</note> them, and forced the woman-like man, and vnmanlike King <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> as he was ſitting and ſpinning among his Curtizans, wittingly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to end his owne life, which (as ſome Authors affirme) was the onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eed that euer hee did to ſhew himſelfe a man, ſpending the reſt of his daies <note place="margin">The Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans &amp; Aſſiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the firſt that made was in the world.</note> more like a woman. Thus were the vain glorious Chaldeans, and arrogant Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yrians the firſt ſeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of ſeditions, the ſtirrers vp of bloudy broyles, maintainers of deadly warres, and vſurpers ouer their neighbours, though happilie not ſo wille, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike, and cruell as they; yet as wiſe, as warlike, and more religious.</p>
            <p>In like violent actions ſucceeded the <hi>Medes,</hi> and <note place="margin">The Perſians, Greekes, and Romanes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in pride, &amp; tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans, Aſſiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans &amp; Meads.</note> 
               <hi>Perſians,</hi> after them the <hi>Greekes,</hi> and <hi>Romanes,</hi> ſo that the worlde hath hitherto neuer wanted ſome one nation: ſometime it hath had mo, that haue beene ſcourges, whippes, and terrours vnto the reſidue. But at this preſent day, whether our age doth want one, eſpecially beautifull <hi>Europe,</hi> in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny quarters, whereof the glorious light of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <note place="margin">At this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern part of Europe affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a proud diſturber, and injurious mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſter of his neighbour Princes.</note> ſhineth moſt cleerely, that ſeeketh to banniſh and blemiſh her ſplendent beautie, that vexeth the other noble princes vniuſtly, diſquieteth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours both by ſea and land maliciouſly, vſurpeth ouer Crownes, kingdomes, and countries moſte
<pb facs="tcp:17071:6"/> impudently, gouerneth his owne tyrannicallie, committeth maſſacres inceſſantly, breatheth out bitter threates opprobriouſly, ſnatcheth at all gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, and aymeth at all with violence, and armes, aske his owne dominions firſt (for hee nameth all how euer it be gotten his own) and next all the eſtates of Chriſtendome will anſwere with one conſent, and readily deſide the controuerſie. But <note place="margin">Papiſtes, or Neuters.</note> ſome will ſay, who either know little, or heare leſſe, or ſee leaſt of all, for that happily, or rather vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, they are of purpoſe ignoraunt, deafe for the nonce, and wilfully blind (as in this point a great number are) Sir I neither know nor heare, nor ſee any ſuch matters in Chriſtendome, as you menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but to make further triall, let vs examine the attemptes and practiſes of all kings chriſtened: and ſee who it is, that is guiltie of theſe moſte heinous <note place="margin">The right tearmes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſantes, and Traytors.</note> crimes you obiect, beginning firſt with the moſte worthie, the king Catholicke, eldeſt in yeares, mightieſt in power, richeſt in ſubſtance, and moſte <note place="margin">The Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to proue the innocencie of king Philip.</note> deuout in religion: He for that he is a catholicke, and piller of the Churche, loueth, imbraceth, and nouriſheth the Goſpell: He for that hee is by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture milde, and taught by Gods lawes not to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeeketh no mans bloud: He for that his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters haue been iuſt, and peaceable, liueth with hys neighbour princes vprightly, and louingly: He for that he cleaueth vnto the Pope, cannot erre, but is full of compaſſion: He for that hee tendreth his <hi>Ieſuites</hi> hath learned to be humble and meeke: He is full of charitie, and therefore not couetous: He is olde and decrepit, and therefore cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade,
<pb facs="tcp:17071:6"/> much leſſe vſurpe, or do violence, all which vntruthes in a word or two, ſhalbe confuted.</p>
            <p>If he did ſincerely loue, imbrace, and nouriſhe <note place="margin">The former reaſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.</note> the Goſpell, would he xxxiii. whole years togither moleſt the Prince, enuie the people, and diſturbe the Realme, that generally aboue all other loueth, <note place="margin">Meant by the Queene and people of England.</note> imbraceth, and nouriſheth the goſpel? If he loued, imbraced, and nouriſhed the Goſpell, woulde hee ſeeke by all meanes poſſible to hinder the rightful poſſeſſion, and orderly proceedings of a king, who <note place="margin">The moſte chriſtian king of France.</note> theſe manie yeares hath impoueriſhed himſelfe by ſeeking to plant the Goſpell, and ſo manie times hath, and yet daily doth fight, and hazardes his <note place="margin">Cuius contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, verum eſt.</note> life for the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>But ſo truely he loueth, imbraceth, and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Goſpell, as he burneth and banniſheth out of his territories, infinite ſwarmes of riche <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſworne enemies to the Goſpel. <note place="margin">The Goſpell willeth vs to yeelde vnto Caeſar thoſe thinges that are Ceſars, and vnto God thoſe thinges that ar Gods: but he teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them all together trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, rancor, and matice a gainſt their Soueraigne. Among all theſe nations the Spaniards ſwordes haue beene buſie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſo he loueth, imbraceth, and nouriſheth the Goſpel, that he maketh his <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and Shaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges forget all Goſpel, and mangleth, and maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creth all true profeſſors of the Goſpell. That hee is milde by nature, and ſeeketh no mans bloud, Firſt aske his ſlaughtered ſonne, and wife, aske the millions of Moores, and poore Portingales, aske thouſands of Neopolitanes, and Dutchmen, aske Frenchmen, and Italians, yea and the Engliſh, that haue been tortured, and tormented to death by him, and they all but that he hath made them ſure inough from crying, would with their wofull cries, and greeuous clamours reſolue you, or at the leaſt all Chriſtendome yet liuing, that haue noted
<pb facs="tcp:17071:7"/> his drifts and dealings theſe fortie yeares, will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie their office? How peaceably, and louingly he liueth with his neighbour Princes: how full of compaſſion, humble and meeke hee is, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee do vſurpe, and offer violence, England, <note place="margin">Each of theſe countries had their partes but theſe 33. whole yeares he hath had continually a fling at Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> France, Flanders, Poland, the Venetians, ech duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in Italie, Aragon, Portugall, Nauarre and Bearne, yea, and the bookes that are daily printed in them, and ſent abroad from them touching our preſent matter doe teſtifie: and hauing ſo many au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentique witneſſes, what neede I more proofe in an open cauſe? Only this leaue I requeſt to thinke that the propheſie that was found in the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <note place="margin">A propheſie found in Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall.</note> of Conimbua in Portingall, in the raign of <hi>Dom Emanuell,</hi> is verified in him, that the little King of <note place="margin">Parrius Rex Auſtri per ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula climata mundi, Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ingenii di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur, ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men omni Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropa fietterro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri vt rector A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerni.</note> the great South, ſhould be renowned through out the world for his pollicie, and redoubted in al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome for his tyranny; for whome (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he poſſeſſeth at this day more large ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, and greater ſtore of wealth, then anie of his progenitors, or any other prince Chriſtian euer did, and al his proud Partizans thundring out whole worldes of threates: little England, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and victorious Queene of England, the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Nobilitie of England, the valiant Gentlemen <note place="margin">If England feare God, and be true within it ſelfe, it may boldly bid a fig for the Spaniard.</note> of England, the true hearted commons of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land relying vpon God the defender of their right, do bid a Figge, in reſpect of anie great danger, or ſtrange detriment, they can inflict either vpon her royall perſon, or her loyall ſubiects at home, or her Maieſties approued friendes abroad, which action that it is both princely, politique, and diſcreet,
<pb facs="tcp:17071:7"/> as alſo chriſtianlike, ſincere, and charitable, ſhall appeare by the ſequell. Firſt therefore to proue <note place="margin">The Spaniards guile.</note> that the Spaniardes, as it is their guiſe, rather thundereth rigorouſly, threatneth terriblie, and ſpitteth out his ſpight vennemouſly, then mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth (as they ſay) good earneſt ſimply, howe euer he holds our Ieſuites in hand, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perſiſt in their wicked exploits: we will be ſo bold, as to conſider his owne domeſticall affaires, the late ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, and croſſe buſineſſe that befell in Aragon, &amp; other places, and ſee whether in likelihood he be able now to performe, as whilome in the eares of <note place="margin">Great garboils of late betwen the Spaniards and the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Portingals &amp; Caſtilions.</note> the world hee boaſted. For who doth not heare that liſteth to hearken after newes, what vncouth troubles, dangerous skirmiſhes, daily mutinies, and plentifull effuſion of bloud, haue lately happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned betweene the Spaniards, and Aragonians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Caſtillions, &amp; their other vaſſals: the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor wherof ſhal briefly be touched. <hi>Antonie Teretz</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The common rumor is for ſtabbing a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie younker fauoured of the King of Spaine.</note> Secretarie to the king of Spaine, vpon what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is yet vncertaine (for that it is the Spaniardes diſſembling nature, to minde and reuenge one thing, but to pretend another) being committed to priſon, found the meanes partly through his wife, who daily had acceſſe vnto him, and partly by his letters directed to his friendes about the Court, that he eſcaped, ſome ſay in the habite of a Countriman, who being ſecretly conueied to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoſa <note place="margin">The occaſion of the firſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in Arago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> in Aragon among his friends, made known vnto them, howe indirectly, or rather iniuriouſly the king and inquiſition proceeded againſt them contrarie to iuſtice, and the priuiledges of their
<pb facs="tcp:17071:8"/> Realme, to what purpoſe they did it, and to what effect it would inſue, if it were not remedied. As of ſmall drops, riſe great flouds, and of a ſparke is kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled a great fire: ſo of this (in mans iudgement, but a ſmall mole-hill is made ſo great a mountaine that it may bee a ſecret iudgement of the Lorde, to cauſe to ſpring from thence, either ſo great a floud, that may drowne all Spaine for their ſinnes, or ſo forcible a light fire, that may purge &amp; purifie them from their dregs.</p>
            <p>But to the matter, newes being brought vnto the King, and inquiſition of the eſcape of the ſecretarie &amp; that he had gotten Aragon, a ſtrong <hi>Mandamus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The light fire of the goſpell</note> was ſealed to the Vice-roy, to make all ſpeedy and diligent ſearch after him: wherein the Vice-roy prooued ſo painefull, that once againe the Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <note place="margin">THe double diligence of the Viceroy.</note> was taken and caſt into priſon, no doubt, but much more narrowly watched then before. The holy Fathers of the Inquiſition, the catercappe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, Doctors (I ſhould ſay) that like bloudy but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, continually thirſt after bloud, thinking them ſelues ſure, and all things in ſafety: whileſt they are preparing to ſit in iudgement vpon the ſaid <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Teretz,</hi> and diſpatch him in the way, were ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly encountred by a multitude that lay cloſely in ambuſhe for the purpoſe, in and about the Cittie from the Countrey and mountaines there about, whereby the Secretarie was re-deliuered, many of the holy Fathers ſlaughtered, their Couches ſome of them burnt, ſome hackt and hewed in peeces, their ſeruants ſcattered, the Kings and Vice-royes powers diſcomfited, and to the number of 150 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:17071:8"/> ſlaine. The King hauing intelligence of this great diſhonour and vnfortunate repulſe, ſtanding vpon thornes till he were reuenged, forthwith diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched a band of 4000. againſt them; who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the boon of a tyrant is bloud, and his grace nothing but death, reſolued euerie man to trie the laſt dice of fortune, and ſo die, then yeelding, bee brought into a ſecond ſlauerie. In fine, ſo well the <note place="margin">The rendering of the citties &amp; kingdomes of Catalonia and valentia.</note> citizens and kingdom of Aragon demeaned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the kings forces, that they drew vnto them the citties and kingdomes of Catalonia, and Valentia alſo: which three kingdomes are vppe in arms againſt the King, partly to reuenge the deaths of thoſe noble perſonages, whome moſt cruelly he murdered: and partly to defend their antient rites, and priuileges: and vpon many and waightie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, haue elected them (as ſome report) a new King.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>The names of the Nobles, whom lately the King of Spaine hath put to death.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The names of the nobles who latelie ſuffered in Spaine.</note>
               </head>
               <label>be theſe.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Duke of Oſſune.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Duke of Ferill.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Countie of Orgus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Countie of Micas, gouernor of Granado.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>ſtrangled and burnt</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Archbiſhop of Corduba con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor to the King.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Biſhop of Cadis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Don Franciſco Lapeto, preſident of the Kings counſell.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Vaſques</hi> Secretarie to the ſtate, is fled with 7. Nobles more, and <hi>Anthany Teretz</hi> alſo, whoſe diſcourſe ye haue heard is fledde, and ſafe with the French King, who is his rightfull Liege. Theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected tumults, and ſudden claps of war, though they haue bin of ſhort continuance, yet haue they bene very comberſome and bitter vnto the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and haue not onely cauſed great hart-burning againſt him with the Laiety, but alſo ſome rancour of the Cleargy, as may appeare by this probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>On <hi>All-Saints</hi> day laſt, there chanced a Ieſuite <note place="margin">A pleaſant, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of a Ieſuite and a frier con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine perſons of ſufficient credite, who haue receiued the truth of all theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> (which order is moſt odible to all other Cloyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers) to preach in Saragoſa before diuers men of account in the citty, who among other matters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan buſily to handle the preſent mutinies, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerent rebellions of the land, againſt their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and holy Fathers of the inquiſition, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the emolument that came by them, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences that would enſue, if they were reſiſted: concluding with this corollarium, that it would be meritorious, both for their bodies &amp; ſoules, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Realme, profitable to themſelues, their wiues, children, and kinſefolkes, yea, and auailable for their landes and liuinges (for which they were now in contention) if they wold quietly lay down thoſe armes, and readilie betake them to the mercy of his Catholique Maieſtie, and fauour of the holy inquiſition. A. Frier happilie hearing him, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie noting more then the common people, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though generally enough was noted) in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonema, or ſhutting vp of his matter, not miſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb facs="tcp:17071:9"/> approched the Pulpit, and ſuddenly threwe a chain or coller of puddings about the Ieſuits neck, <note place="margin">A pudding is too good meat for a trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Ieſuite.</note> crying out good people, heere is meete dinner for the Ieſuits good ſermon: which deed notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there were preſent men of authority of the Citty, and queſtionleſſe very many of the currant ſtamps, yet generally it was ſo well taken, that out of the Church, the Ieſuit was haled into the ſtreet, and there diſguiſed in a fooles coat, carried vppon mens ſhoulders to bee ſcorned vp and downe the Citty, and whether hee eſcaped with life, is not yet ſignified. And here by the way I wiſh all men, that either heare or read theſe truthes, truly and duly to conſider, what great cauſe <hi>Don Philip</hi> of Spain hath either to pretend, or practiſe any inuaſion, vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <note place="margin">K. Philip if he looke about him, at this time hathſmal cauſe to broch new broiles.</note> Prince forraine this yeare, hauing ſo much ado at home, not onely with his temporaltie, but alſo with his darling and ſweet nurſerie his ſacred and ſpotles ſpiritualtie. Thus far concerning the ſtate and affaires of Aragon: nowe let vs ſee what is and hath beene done this yeare in Portingall. A <note place="margin">Roceio is an open place, where gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men walke for their pleſure in Lisbon.</note> Portingal gentleman walking in the Roceio of Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, eſpied a baſe Caſtilion of ſuch proud and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumtuous demenor, ſo fantaſticall in his attire, lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in his looks, and ſlow in his pace, (as though he had bin treading of meaſures) could not long bear him, but bearded him, and iuſtled him, wherevpon <note place="margin">The originall of the laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions in Portingall.</note> the mater was debated by Stafford law, the Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſlaine, and the Spaniard eſcaped into the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Immediatly certaine Portingall Gentlemen of his familiars ſwore reuenge, &amp; not long ſince haue had their wils. For on S. Mathews day laſt, finding
<pb facs="tcp:17071:10"/> a crue of Caſtilions reuelling in a brothell houſe, ſuddenlie ſet vpon, and ſlewe fiue of them, which cauſed the other Caſtillions of the Caſtle to come downe in extreame heat of choller, and offer great violence through the cittie, vntill the great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Portingals that were haſtilie ſwarmed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, made them betake them to their heeles, and euer ſince more watchfullie, &amp; warilie guard their <note place="margin">But thus it is not ended: for ſince we haue had knowledg of diuers other bickerings.</note> caſtle. The mater being brought in queſtion before the Cardinal (who now a while keepeth warm the K. of Portingals ſeat,) &amp; being found that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards were chief maſters of miſrule and miſchiefe, (as they are alwaies) they were puniſhed ſeuerelie, but all in vaine: for old rankor is not eaſilie forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <note place="margin">A Paradox. King Philip to inioy the crown of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe three moſt damnable iniquities, firſt he betraied to death his own Nephew, next ſet paking the Cardinal, and laſtly exiled and keepeth in exile the right heire.</note> nor the antient malice between thoſe two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions lightlie forgiuen. For it is impoſſible, &amp; may paſſe for a Paradox to thinke that thoſe two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Portingall and Spaniard will euer be fullie reconciled. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as often as either they ſhal remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or their cronicles report the fraudulent feats of falſe <hi>Philip</hi> againſt his neighbour K. and kingly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Don Sebaſtion</hi> ſo braue a yong prince, &amp; only hope of the Portingals, record the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned vſurping of the ſpitefull Spaniards, &amp; miſerable exile of <hi>Don Anthony</hi> lawful, and indubitant heire, now fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and foſtered by her Maieſtie: ſo often as they ſhal either ſpeake, or thinke vpon the curſed acts of <hi>Chriſtophero de Moyra</hi> one of the Kings fauorites: as often as they ſhall either heare or thinke vpon the heapes of their poore countrey men, that haue bin within this 13. yeares moſt deſperatly murthered, and of their owne intollerable ſeruitude they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure at this inſtant, they will haue as good and fell
<pb facs="tcp:17071:10"/> ſtomaks; as euer they had at the Ile of <hi>Terferes,</hi> what time the braue and wiſe gentleman <hi>Don Cyprian Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guredo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſto de Moyra ſent a counterfeit cooke into France to poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Don Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. This gouernor gaue the king of Spain great battailes, and ouercame in both, liuing now with his King in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> 
               <hi>Vaſconſalus</hi> was gouernour there to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards coſt, to rip out their harts, and eat them with ſalt. Wherein I aduertiſe all thoſe of our Nation, that without any ſufficient triall of their deteſtable deeds, and knowledge of their crabbed nature, are ſuch great friends, and ſtout fauorites of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the world, not to bee deceiued, but as they be men, and ſhould haue the ſpirite of reaſon, ſo to bee gouerned and guided by reaſon. Suppoſe the Spaniard as they wiſh (but God be praiſed he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie far from) ſhould make a conqueſt in this land, and bring all to his bay, as hee hath done in other countries ouer whome hee vſurpeth: Would hee (tro yee) ſpare this more then them? No: hee will finde fiue hundred times more cauſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce and ranſacke our citties, to pill and pole our country, to murther and maſſacre our people, then theirs. For they were his neighbours; we meer ſtrangers: they haue bene ſometime his friends; wee alwaies (as he counteth) ſworne enemies: they are of his owne religion, wee altogeather contrary: they haue the Pope to mittigate his wrath, if hee be to fierce; wee haue both Pope and Pope-lings to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe him vnto further ire, that hee may be more frowarde: ſo that whatſoeuer the Pope and hee could doe, that they would doe ſay they) promiſe they, ſweare they neuer ſo much to the contrarie) and whatſoeuer they will doe, may not bee gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid as vnlawfull. Wherefore let all Engliſh hearts and true hearted Engliſh-men, ſay with the Poet.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17071:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurea libertas gemma precioſior omni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whileſt they haue it, imbrace it, &amp; not betray it, but hazard lands, liues, lims &amp; all, to maintain it. Finally, let thoſe regions, ouer whome the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard alreadie tyranizeth, be exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples vnto vs, whoſe cofers are alreadie impoueriſhed, whoſe people are mightily impaired, whoſe liues are not theyr owne, whoſe landes vpon euerie light quarrell are confiſcate, whoſe antient-rightes are contemned, peculiar priuiledges infringed, wholeſome lawes violated, and all in all corrupted: then may we cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly ſay, God the Lord of hoſtes (who is, and hath alwaies been our defender) is our right, and cheerfully vaunt, <hi>a Fig for the Spaniard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We haue hetherto diſcuſſed howe vnlike, and vnable the Spaniardes is in reſpect of the foreſayd troubles, which as yet on no part are fully pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to purſue his determination: nowe let vs prie a litle more narrowly into matters of no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and by examining them wee may eaſily coniecture, what he is able to effect. The ſcarcitie therefore of bread, and defect of all other ſtore of <note place="margin">Wonderfull great dearth throughout all Spaine.</note> victuall, wherwith Spaine, eſpecially the ſea-coaſts thereof, this preſent yeare haue beene plagued, woulde rather haue beene a terrible warning to anie other Prince of corrigible nature, to haue humbled himſelfe vnto almightie God, and to continue in praier for the auoydance of ſo great a miſerie, then to prepare and threaten bloudy wars againſt his neighbour Princes, better able for the preſent to maugre, and indure armes then he: yea
<pb facs="tcp:17071:11"/> the flouriſhing kingdome of Naples, which for his <note place="margin">God puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſometime for the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions of the Prince.</note> woonderfull fertilitie was wont to be tearmed the Garden of the world, hath theſe two yeares ſo ill proſpered, not onely in her corne, and fruites, but alſo in her vintage, and other prouiſion, that it is found not to yeeld the third part that it was wont: whereby the people periſh moſte lamentably, the <note place="margin">Nero Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of Rome, when hee ſaw the Citie fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with fire, laughed and ſoong verſes contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Troy.</note> land is waſted pitifully, and all in all lament ruful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: onely <hi>Philip</hi> who ſhould be more grieued, and penſiue then the reſt, like his great grandſier <hi>Nero,</hi> when he ſawe Rome on fire, is ſo farre from mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that he rather mocketh, and triumpheth <hi>riſit Sardonico.</hi> But ſay that neither theſe plagues of ſwelling ſedition, or pinching famine, happily ſent by God himſelfe to none other ende, but to relent his ſtonie heart, and ſet him at peace, with other Princes that ſeek after, and delight in peace, can quallifie his hautie humour, or quench his hot deſire of reuenge: Let vs yet weigh if there be not occaſions of as great moment to moue and molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him, except he meane his people, ſhippes, artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie, and warlike furniture ſhould rather periſh by warre, then conſumed through famine. Who is <note place="margin">In Flanders, France, and England.</note> ignorant of the great ſlaughters of Spaniards, that haue beene committed within theſe foure yeares? who is ignorant of the huge loſſe, both of men and ſhips he hath ſuſtained in this laſt Indian voyage? who doth not knowe that he that inioyeth much, hath need of <hi>Argus</hi> eyes, <hi>Mercuries</hi> braine, and <hi>Hercules</hi> ſtrength to maintaine it? and who doth not knowe that his ſtorehouſe of Sicilie for this <note place="margin">The Sicillons made him plainly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, they had not corne enough for themſelues.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:17071:12"/> yeare is emptie? Seeing then Spaine cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſuſtaine, muche leſſe relieue, or repaire ſuche infinite loſſes both of men, ſhippes, artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and all other prouiſion of victualles, within <note place="margin">The Duke of Florence will haue a ſaying to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Lantado, for abuſing his colours, defeating the people of the prouiſion of their corne, and manie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iniuries The laſt pope finely, and wittily deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the king of Spaine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie requeſtes: Theſe and ſuch like dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges haue cauſed the deathes of 5. Popes within theſe 17. monethes.</note> her owne boundes, ſeeing ſuche innumerable cares depend on their neckes, and that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not indure them without the aſſiſtance of others: Let vs nowe reaſon what poſſibilitie they haue to be ſuccoured by others, and beginne firſt with their owne neighbours. It is poſſible they may command a few hungerſterued ſlaues in Naples, and the partes adioyning (whereof they haue the gouernment) but in other partes of Italie, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Genua, Florence, and Venice, where he is loued, as the Diuell loueth holy water: he may command, and go without, and intreating, obtain as man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bands of men, and thouſands of crowns, (which ſome ſuſpect was the deathe of the laſt Pope) as a chicken can holde in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fiſt. As for France and Flanders, therein his iolly brauo haue ſuch gallant counterbuffes daily, the one part by the moſt Chriſtian mirrour of chyualrie, the french king, the other by the puiſſant and politicke prince <hi>Graue Maurice,</hi> that they looke for aid of him, who <note place="margin">Sigiſmund king of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes of the Ieſuites at Gacow, wher they haue beaten downe and raſed the Churches of the reformed religion.</note> is himſelfe aidleſſe, rather then anie way finde themſelues of ſtrength to ſuccour their hapleſſe Monarches. Likewiſe Germanie, and eſpecially Poland, in manie corners, whereof he hath cloſely couched his rabbles of <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and ſet all in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores, are ſo vnable, and vnapt to ſuccor him, that they are skant able to defend themſelues. Finally
<pb facs="tcp:17071:12"/> from England, wherinto dayly he ſendeth whol heards, and hundreds of <hi>Ieſuites, Seminaries,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to diſturb our peace: althogh her Maieſtie euer louing, &amp; longing after peace, hath ſought alwaies rather to gratulate him, then anie way to grieue him: yet in anie of theſe attempts he is to hope for no helpe, except hee woulde imploy <note place="margin">Philip man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Iohn Marilian hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Embaſſadour three whole years at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople to increate for peace, which at length was obtained in ſuche ſorte, that neither Chriſtian nor Turke thoght it would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, for both Princes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied them ſelues to the time, rather then that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them deſired anie friendſhip of other.</note> his forces to better vſe, then onely to ſeeke the ſpoyle, and effuſion of chriſtian bloud. Princes of former yeares liuing together in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, and linked with the ſweete chaine of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-like charitie, were woont to leuie all their powers againſt the vntamed Pagons, and enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Chriſtianitie, but hee hath beene lately conuinced to doe quite contrarie: howe then of Chriſtians can he looke for courteſie. But ſome will obiect, and ſay, Tuſh <hi>Philip</hi> is ric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he poſſeſſeth whole Mines of coine, he is the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cheuallier, he needeth no mans courteſie. Let him but holde vp his finger, hee ſhall haue friendes, followers, and ſouldiers inowe: this argument is both weake, and ſlender, and hath partly beene refelled before: therefore in three wordes with the Poet, thus briefly I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it. <hi>Malo virum pecunia, quam pecuniam viro indigentem.</hi> Hetherto concerning hys buſineſſe at home, and condition with his bordering neighbours. Nowe let vs looke what hope the Spaniardes hath to enterpriſe anie inuaſion, or conqueſt in reſpect of England.</p>
            <p>The firſt, and chiefeſt reaſons therfore, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:17071:13"/> his Partizans, and partakers vſe to induce him, and hale him on (whether of his owne will he is readily inough inclined) are theſe three <note place="margin">Three reaſons our Engliſh Traytours vſe to vrge to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip.</note> in number. The firſt is drawne from the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her Maieſties Nauie. The ſecond of a ſuppoſed euill contentment of a number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the land to ſerue the Queene, and hir go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment againſt her enemies. Laſtly, and moſt principally of a great ſtrong partie, that will be found heere in the fauour of them for religion <note place="margin">A meere fable and of no likelihood.</note> that wil take armes againſt her highneſſe, vppon the ſight of the Catholique Nauie on the coaſts of England: all which that they are but imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſurmiſes, and vntrue reportes, hath alreadie bene proued, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1588. at what time the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious force, and forcible courage of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſufficiently appeared, when as at the firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the mightie Spaniſh <hi>Armada,</hi> our <note place="margin">Some ſay it was their Viceadmirall: but how euer it was, a moſt huge barge.</note> ſimple Fleete of Fiſh-boates (as it pleaſed them to tearme it) tooke their Viceadmirall, and for the ſpace of 8. or 9. dayes togither, ſo ſcattered, ſlaughtered, ſunk, &amp; chaſed them, that they were forced to flie from the coaſtes of Flanders neere Calice, towards the vnknowne parts of the cold North: all their hopes, all their buildings, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded but vppon a conceited conqueſt, vtterly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne and (as it were) with an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, all their coſtes, and comfortes by the omnipotent, and outſtretched arme of God, brought to the ground. As to the ſecond branch of their hope depending vpon opinion of ſome
<pb facs="tcp:17071:13"/> great miſcontentment of manie, and ſundry per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the Queenes Maieſtie, the proofe of the contrarie ſo appeared the ſelfe ſame yeare, both of her Maieſties actions to maintaine the liking of all her people, and of the generall ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deuotion ſhewed to her Maieſtie, by all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, Noble and meane, rich and poore, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantes and papiſts, as I thinke no prince chriſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned euer had greater cauſe of comfort in her people.</p>
            <p>Now to the laſt point, that there ſhalbe found heere in the Realme a ſtrong partie of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques to ioyne againſt the Queene, and aſſiſt the inuaders, by the former relations of the generall great, and feruent loue of all the land toward her excellent Maieſtie, of the great offers of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, made by the whol Nobilitie of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewes of braue men, and ſtately ſteedes, of their infinite coſtes and expences, of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall forwardneſſe of the commons in all actions, and of their prompt mindes to execute all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of good ſubiectes, euen vnto the loſſe of their liues, this their foundation is weake, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and of no force, and therefore no waie to be feared.</p>
            <p>We haue already proued by manie reaſons, and thoſe ſubſtantial inough, how vnlike and vnable the Spaniard is, both in reſpect of himſelfe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the helpe of his neighbors, and in reſpect <note place="margin">The Spaniard vnlike to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer England for three rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> of our own right, and might, to maſter and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt vs with anie huge hurt, or ſinguler ſcath: all
<pb facs="tcp:17071:14"/> which notwithſtanding are thus, for that we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſee man propoſeth, but God diſpoſeth, to be vnderſtoode, and reſtrained that they may and ſhall proue true, ſo long as we ſerue God truely, <note place="margin">Si Deus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum quis contra nos. The Spaniard is not yet brought ſo low, but that he may riſe, rage and reigne again, if we be not thankefull to almightie God, pliable to our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries peace, and watchfull for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. Nam qui ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel caepit eſſe hoſtis, &amp; ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum erit, ſi nactus fuerit occaſionem.</note> liue in loyall ſeruice, and dutifull obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our Prince louingly, honour our Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates reuereutly, liue togither charitably, and detect and diſcrie wicked treaſons, and obſtinate traytors willingly: otherwiſe the Lord will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, reuiue, and increaſe the Spaniards ſtrength exceedingly, cauſe him preuaile mightely, and triumph ouer vs ſpightfully, ſo that no man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt all that hath beene ſpoken, is ſo farre to preſume, that either he omit anie iote of chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anlike ſeruice toward almightie God, or loyall obedience toward his naturall Prince, or ſacred honour toward the ſupriour Magiſtrate, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere loue towardes his home borne neighbours, but as wee were ſeene not yet a Prentice yeares <note place="margin">Anno 1588</note> ſithence, (at what time the minds of many were daunted with a ſodaiue feare of the enemie) to ſerue God deuoutly, obey our prince cheerfully, reuerence the Magiſtrat diſcretly, &amp; liue and loue together faithfully, ſo to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, &amp; (if need once againe require) to ſpend lands, lims, liues and all as then wee profered readilie for God and our countrey, and not to hatch treaſons cloſely, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh traitors couertly, ſuccour fugitiues wilfullie, or ſupport ſhameles runnegats continually, men of no conſcience, ſworne enemies to God, their Prince, and countrey: which that we may do to
<pb facs="tcp:17071:14"/> the glorie of the eternall GOD, comfort of our dread Soueraigne, ioy of our vigilant Magiſtrats weeding out of hypocriticall rebels, wholeſome <note place="margin">Thus if we doe, then may we boldly bid a Fig for the Spaniard, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a figge of his owne, or, as they ſay vna higa Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians.</note> preſeruation of mutuall charity at home, &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conſolation of our poore diſtreſſed bretheren abroad, the Lord of hoſts in mercy grant for his ſweet ſons ſake, to whom with his Chriſt our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peacemaker, &amp; the holy Ghoſt our comforter, be al honour, lawd, praiſe, and thankeſgiuing for all his vnſpeakeable louing kindneſſes extended on the ſinfull people of England both nowe and for euer, and let all that feare his name, and wiſhe the bleſſed peace of his Church, ſay in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout zeale, and zealous deuotion of ſpirit,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
